<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Steph Explores</title>
    <description>Exploring trails and waterways in Manitoba and northwestern Ontario</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 02:02:07 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 02:02:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>North Face Tadpole 2 Tent</title>
        <description>North Face Tadpole 2 Tent and Footprint

Our first trip out with this tent was in the middle of February. We spent a weekend at our friend’s cabin on West Hawk Lake and with the balmy winter temperatures we figured we may as well give winter camping a shot. Instead of snow we woke up to sleet and rain, signalling an early end to winter.

While researching tents my main focus was looking for a small backpacking tent that we could bring to Iceland. The Tadpole 2 checked all of our boxes and ended up being the perfect fit for us. We took the tent on the Mantario Trail on May Long Weekend and were once again greeted with no-so-fortunate weather. As a result, we had a few rainy and wet nights to test out its durability. Unfortunately on this trip we forgot the pegs so we only had a couple borrowed pegs to secure the vestibule open. We were a little concerned that the side panels would soak through at night but we woke up warm and dry every morning!

The two person tent has a trail weight of 3 lbs 15 oz and costs around $430. Word on the street is that they’re no longer manufacturing the tent but you may still be able to pick it up in-store or online. I was able to snag a great deal on the Tadpole 2 footprint from the Prairie Summit Shop.

What I Loved:

  
    Small footprint – Capable of fitting in small isolated spots
  
  
    Roomy - We fit two regular sized sleeping pads as well as two bags inside the tent at the base of our feet
  
  
    Weather proof – The tent held up in the snow/sleet and the rain
  
  
    Pole construction – The hubbed poles connect to the tent using pull and secure gadgets, they felt very stable!
  


Critiques:

  
    Single vestibule - I usually prefer having access on both sides of the tent but the added benefit is an even smaller footprint
  
  
    Initial setup - Set up was fussy at first, but we had things down pat by the second night
  


Overall this has been a great tent for us so far. I have no concerns about its ability to hold up in windy and wet Icelandic weather!
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-tadpole-2-tent</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-tadpole-2-tent</guid>
        
        <category>The North Face</category>
        
        <category>Tents</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kodiak Acadia Hiking Boots</title>
        <description>Kodiak Acadia Boots

“No Winnipeger alive has ever experienced the kind of winter we’ve just survived” – CBC Manitoba describes the winter of 2014 in Winnipeg, Manitoba, and boy were they right. Water pipes across the city froze, leaving thousands of Winnipegers without running water.  Temperatures routinely dropped below -30C and there were frigid nights where the windchill took the temperature to -46C. Needless to say, it was COLD!

But, and there is a but to this story, my feet stayed dry and warm thanks to my Kodiak Acadia boots. I’ve included some highlights below.

Style: These are the most fashionable “hiking” boots I’ve ever seen. Granted, I would only take them on light hikes. Trust me – I can speak from experience. I wore these on my first 60km+ hiking trip through the rain which wasn’t my smartest decision to date.

Durability: These are great for everyday wear – in the city, camping, 20 km hikes. During the aforementioned 60 km hike I attempted to dry my boots out over a fire. Ten minutes later they were smoking as I scorched the mink oil from the leather. Apparently they don’t survive being cooked, but most boots won’t.

Warmth: SO WARM. No complaints.

Waterproof: I’ve walked through puddles and have survived without any leaks. I wouldn’t recommend slugging through bogs.

Thing to improve: I find these boots lack good support. An improved insole would make these boots the cream of the crop.
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/kodiak-acadia-hiking-boots</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/kodiak-acadia-hiking-boots</guid>
        
        <category>North Face</category>
        
        <category>Bags</category>
        
        <category>Camping</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Osprey Ariel AG 65 Women’s Backpack</title>
        <description>Osprey Ariel AG 65 Women’s Backpack

I tried on quite a few bags before landing on this pack and I’m quite happy with my decision. When we first began trying on bags we took a trip down to MEC. I tried on a few brands, including their MEC bags, a Black Diamond bag and a Deuter bag. None of the bags fit me right, either hitting me awkwardly at the hips or gaping far from my lower back.

When I got home I did some research on how to fit a bag. The first recommendation that I came across was to measure the length of your torso. I grabbed a tape measure and realized I have an incredibly short torso (less than 15 inches)! This is on the small size for women’s bags so I had to make sure the brand of bag I purchased had a women’s XS.

Pros

  Wide opening at the top
  Mesh elastic pocket at the front for quick grab-and-go items
  Side entry zipper – makes it so much easier so you don’t have to open your bag every time
  Lower zippered bottom section that can be sectioned off (great for wet clothes &amp;amp; gear)
  Inward synching hip belt


Cons

  Top pocket is quite large. I found if you packed it too full it would push my head forward while hiking.
  Shoulder straps could have tightened a little more. They fit me perfectly fully tightened but I’m worried they may stretch out over time.


In comparison to the North Face Terra 65 that Erik picked up it seems MUCH larger. Honestly, this bag felt like I was putting on my turtle shell every morning. It was comfy and fit perfectly! I have no complaints so far.
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/msr-whisperlite-campstove</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/msr-whisperlite-campstove</guid>
        
        <category>tag 1</category>
        
        <category>tag 2</category>
        
        <category>tag 3</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Woman's Atlas Elektra 11 Snowshoes</title>
        <description>This is an H1

This is an H2

This is an H6

Markdown Syntax cheatsheet click here
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/womans-atlas-elektra-11-snowshoes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/womans-atlas-elektra-11-snowshoes</guid>
        
        <category>North Face</category>
        
        <category>Bags</category>
        
        <category>Camping</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>North Face Base Camp Duffel</title>
        <description>This is an H1

This is an H2

This is an H6

Markdown Syntax cheatsheet click here
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-base-camp-duffel</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-base-camp-duffel</guid>
        
        <category>The North Face</category>
        
        <category>Bags</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The North Face Dryzzle Rain Jacket</title>
        <description>The North Face Dryzzle Rain Jacket

I purchsed this jacket….
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-dryzzle-rain-jacket</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/the-north-face-dryzzle-rain-jacket</guid>
        
        <category>The North Face</category>
        
        <category>Jackets</category>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rushing River in the Winter</title>
        <description>Rushing River
February 2016

February is always a crazy month for me. There’s quite a few birthdays (including my own), planning for the Delta Waterfowl Fundraising Dinner and then gearing up for the climbing competition in March. In early February, two girlfriends and I took a break from the hectic part of life and did a Sunday road trip out to Rushing River Provincial Park.

Bailey and Mel picked me up from my apartment first thing Sunday morning and with our snowshoes and white cheddar KD packed, we made the drive out to Ontario. The weather was beautiful with temperatures in the low minus digits and the sun shining. When we pulled up to the park we were the only car in the lot which was fairly expected in the middle of winter.



We unpacked our snowshoes, layered up and stuck some snacks in our backpack. We decided to hike the Lower Rapids Trail before lunch and headed for the trail across the highway. The Lower Rapids Trail is probably the most popular hike at the park, it’s short, accessible right off the highway and not challenging at all. That however, does not mean its lacking beauty, especially in the winter. The open water rushing against the snow filled banks is a beautiful scene.

After spending some time lounging in the snow and taking photos, we continued back to the car to pick up our stove and supplies for lunch. We ran into a group packing up and loading their cross country skies into their car. Apparently the roads within the park are groomed as ski trails all winter long, with an attendant comes out every Friday to maintain them. The Park’s website says there are 16 kilometres of groomed trails at a variety of difficulties! We decided to snowshoe along the trails to find a campsite down by the water for lunch. After stopping by a few sites we decided to head across the frozen lake for better prospects.

Across the lake we found a secluded spot warmed by the afternoon sunlight. We started up the stove for some coffee and hot chocolate and then continued with lunch. After stuffing our faces with white cheddar mac and cheese and chicken salad sandwiches we decided to snowshoe back to the car. Driving 6 hours definitely makes for a long day but it was definitely worth it.
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/hike/rushing-river-in-the-winter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/hike/rushing-river-in-the-winter</guid>
        
        
        <category>hike</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Canoeing Little Limestone Lake</title>
        <description>Little Limestone Lake - Manitoba’s Gem

September 2017

I was probably 17 the first time I saw a picture of Little Limestone Lake. I recall flipping through a coffee table book at my friend’s house, showcasing hidden gems in Manitoba. I’m sure that my reaction was the same as anyone’s the first time that they see a photo of the lake, I just had to get there – it looked exactly like the Caribbean!



Fast forward 5 years and I was sitting in a class at university. One of my classmates started talking about their volunteer work with the Manitoba Chapter of Canadian Parks and Wilderness Society (CPAWS). He explained their efforts around raising awareness for Little Limestone Lake and provided us with a hardcopy postcard to mail to our local politicians.

Little Limestone Lake is noted as the largest marl lake in the world. The CPAWS website is a great resource if anyone is interested in finding out more information on the lake. In short, marl is created by the precipitation of calcium carbonate which is found in limestone. On summer days, an increase in water temperature and pH can trigger this reaction which results in a change to the colour of the water. There are many marl likes located around the world in the U.S. Midwest, Europe, Himalayas, Ireland, etc. but I has been document that Little Limestone Lake has the most dramatic colour changes.

In 2007, Little Limestone Lake was designated as a park reserve which provided interim protection for the lake and up to 100 metres of the surrounding shoreline. In 2011, with the efforts of CPAWS, Mosakahiken Cree Nation and Nature Manitoba, Little Limestone Lake was designated as a provincial park. A scientific study on the lake helped to identify the need for a larger provincial park boundary in order to protect the health of the lake.
In August 2015, I finally made the trip out there with the help of newly gifted roof rack and loaned canoe. Information on the lake and camping is pretty much non-existent on the internet. I was able to locate some minimal information on fishing forums and by speaking with Manitoba Parks staff. On Friday night I learned how to strap my canoe down and by Saturday morning my boyfriend were making the 5.5 hour (40 km past Grand Rapids, MB) drive north on Highway 6 to the lake. When you’re close to the lake you should notice a sign on the left of the highway indicating the turnoff. At the end of the road there was a large opening with some campfire pits and a few places to park. When we arrived we were greeting by a swarm of black flies and expected that this would be the demise of our first trip in Northern Manitoba. We quickly unpacked the car and got the canoe loaded.

Once we got on the water the flies quickly disappeared and the beauty of the lake took over. It was hard to believe that we were in Manitoba. We continued across the lake and decided our best bet would be to follow the shoreline to find a good camping spot. We spent the next three hours, in and out of bays, hoping in and out of the canoe. Most of the shoreline was filled with vegetation and had very narrow rocky beaches, and unfortunately not so camping spots. We finally settled on a small flat rock as the evening started setting in and we set up our tent.

The next two mornings I would wake up with the same astonishment over the view from our tent. We ended up paddling for most of the next day and discovered two other really nice campsites that looked as though they had been previously used (fire pits, etc.). We were able to make it back to our campsite just in time as a strong thunderstorm rolled through. The light from the storm lit up the lake even more than imaginable. We hunkered down in the tent for the rest of the evening and let the storm play out. The next morning we kept on betting when we should make the paddle home. We started out when the rain began to die down but were hit with some heavy showers and large waves as we were crossing the lake.

Nonetheless it was a great trip to Little Limestone Lake and I would absolutely recommend it everyone.

Some tips for the trip:

  Bring bear spray and camp smart – as with all backcountry camping, be prepared! At a distance we encountered a bear swimming across the lake on our paddle back.
  Bring a camera – you’ll want to take lots of photos, trust me.
  Do some exploring – the lake is pretty big. We were only able to explore one large bay of the lake due to the rainy weather. We hear there’s a hidden waterfall at one of the outlets of the lake!
  Get a license and go fishing – you’ll find lighter coloured fish due to the minerals in the lake. Watch the following video for some sneak peaks at the fishing up there: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AY8-H-RzlPU
  Be respectful of Mosakahiken Cree territory and of the lake – check out a map before you go and be mindful of where you’re camping. Ask for permission to camp and please leave nothing behind, the beauty of this lake needs to be preserved.

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2015 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/canoeing-little-limestone-lake</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/canoeing-little-limestone-lake</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Icelandic Waterfalls</title>
        <description>Our top three waterfalls in Iceland:


  
    Aldeyjarfoss: Located in north Iceland, in the Lake Myvatn area. After dinner at Godafoss we headed towards Aldeyjarfoss. The highway soon turned to gravel roads and lupine covered fields. The road is restricted to 4WD vehicles but you could technically park and walk a short distance in a 2WD.  There were only a few cars in the parking lot when we arrived. You could hear the waterfall over in the distance but couldn’t see it. We hiked a short trail down and reached the magnificent waterfall. The dark, perfectly rectangular basalt columns framed the mesmerizing waterfall. We camped the night in the parking lot and were lucky enough to be the only vehicles there.
  
  
    Háifoss: Located in south Iceland, we visited this waterfall on the first evening of our road trip. We arrived shortly after 1:00 am and there were already a couple other camper vans in the parking lot. We decided to crash for the night and woke up early to see the waterfall for the first time. It’s easy to be blown away by the height of the waterfall, at 122 metres, it takes the record for the second highest waterfall in Iceland. There is also a neighbouring waterfall a short distance from Háifoss called Granni.  The two waterfalls definitely made a picturesque sight. As we were walking around a helicopter flew over the falls and landed on a couple hundred metres from us, what a way to experience Iceland!
  
  
    Name Unknown - East Fjords: Located on the East Fords, this waterfall was found during an unexpected roadside lunchbreak. Erik was able to climb down to the base of the river before it dropped off into the waterfall. As per most waterfall stops, you could see me hovering far from the edge telling him to be safe. I hope you guys find this beauty of a waterfall and get out to explore it! It’s located somewhere past Seyðisfjörður.
  

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/iceland-waterfalls</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/iceland-waterfalls</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Laugavegur Trek</title>
        <description>Laugavegur Trek

The Laugavegur Trek is a 55 kilometre (km) trail that traverses across the southern highlands of Iceland. Most hikers start the hike in Landmannalaugar and end in Þórsmörk. If you’re feeling up for it you can continue on the Fimmvörðuháls hike  to Skogar.

You can drive or take a bus to both Landmannalaugar and Þórsmörk. Either location would be a great two-day trip if you’re not interested in completing the hike but I would highly recommend it.

We decided to camp along the trail and did not pay to stay in the huts. We had originally read online that you could use the kitchens within the huts even if you were camping but that turned out to not be true. You can still use the outdoor kitchen and washroom facilities. Camping cost us about $10 US per person and showers ranged in price, usually $2 – 5 US depending on the length of time you spent in there. Be prepared to pack out all of your garbage, you are not allowed to leave anything at the huts – and rightly so, I imagine it’s a long drive up there for the staff!

Day 1: Landmannalaugar to Álftavatn (24 km)

We left for the Laugavegur Trek early Sunday morning with the plan to reach Þórsmörk in three days.  The ride out was our first look at the Icelandic landscape and boy, was it amazing – moss so vibrant it looked fake, steaming soils and enough sheep to outnumber the tourists (almost, but not quite!). We arrived in Landmannalaugar at 9:00 am and the rain was pouring down. We decided it would be a good idea to take cover, repack and eat some oatmeal before beginning the hike. Luckily we chose to do this as we realized the gas canister that we had purchased did not fit our stove. The lovely people working at the Landmannalaugar hut swapped out our canister for the correct one. Phew! Or else we would have been eating cold dehydrated food for the remainder of the hike.

As soon as we started hiking we we’re already in awe of the views, rhyolite mountains, steaming hot springs and groups of hikers galore. As we starting ascending the Brennisteinsalda Volcano the crowds began to wean out and the colours became more spectacular. The landscape truly looked like an oil painting with varying colours created by sulphur, lava, moss and iron. Quickly the colourful mountains were replaced by black rocks, snow and steep ascents. As we descended into Hrafntinnusker hut the weather looked less than ideal. The winds were pretty strong and it was still rainy and cold. We stopped in the doorway of the hut for a quick break to eat and warm up. It was lovely chatting with people from around the world. We ended up meeting an Australian couple who were also making the decision to continue onto the next hut and decided that would be the best idea while our energy levels were still up! We were happy with our decision to keep on going as we walked past other hikers setting up on the rocky, snowy ground.

We traversed across snowy fields, climbed up and down more hills and hiked into a lush landscape on our way to Álftavatn. There is an amazing vantage point overlooking the lake and hilly landside where the hut was located. After a cold stream crossing and a hike along a dirt road, we made it to the hut. The rain had calmed down during the second part of the day so it was enjoyable to cook dinner, sip on some highland whisky and slowly set up our tent.

Day 2: Álftavatn to Emstrur (16 km)

We woke up late on Day 2 and lazed around in the tent to see if the rain would die down. By the time we started packing up we were one of the few tents remaining. As soon as you leave the hut you climb a short distance and then immediately cross a glacier stream. After speeding through the water, we quickly put our boots on to keep in front of the crowds. There were a number of stream crossings on the way to Emstrur, some with strong current and water up to your waist! After crossing a few bridges and seeing some beautiful waterfalls, we entered into a barren mars like landscape. If you’ve ever felt like you were moving forward but stuck in the same location, this would be that place. We were tired and ready to finish as our eyes and teeth filled with dirt and grit from the blowing black sands. In the distance we could see another pair of hikers ahead of us on the trail. I attempted to measure their distance and time while we snacked. Based on my calculations we were aiming to get into the hut before 7 pm. When we finally saw the hut in the distance we could hardly wait to set up camp and enjoy some dinner.  We found a beautiful spot for our tent that overlooked the glaciers in the distance; not a bad way to end the night.

Day 3: Emstrur to Þórsmörk (16 km)
The next and last day we woke up to sun! This was great as we were able to dry out some articles of persistently wet clothing and enjoyed the hike with one less layer. Grabbing a hot shower at the hut we felt refreshed and on our way. Shortly after leaving the hut we reached a canyon where we spent some time taking photos and exploring the lush scenery. As the trail continues it stretches along the Myrdalsjokull glacier, giving you a great views as you hike. Thorsmork is located in a lush valley under the glaciers Eyjafjallajokull and Myrdalsjokull. After two cold river crossings we entered a dense birch forest and knew we were close. When we arrived at the hut we immediately started looking for a nice place to set up our tent. We were taking the following day as a rest day in Thorsmork before continuing onto the Fimmvörðuháls hike so having a nice home base was the plan. We found a secluded spot nestled along a stream with amazing views of Eyjafjallajokull and Myrdalsjokull. Thorsmork is a beautiful location for day hikes. The Thorsmork hut had a “general shop” with snacks, drinks and some shelf stable foods. We were able to get some chips and pop as a treat at the end of our hike which was a nice luxury. The next day was pretty rainy but we were able to some short hikes in the area. The most rewarding hike was a short climb on Valahnukar. The trail starts and ends at the hut and goes almost straight up. At the end you reach a beautiful 360 degree view of Thorsmork valley. The braided rivers below, glaciers that appear close enough to touch and terrifying cliffs that drop suddenly to valley bottom. We spent a few hours up there just marvelling at the views.

The Laugavegur Trek lived up to its hype. While not an overly challenging hike it did provide a variety of landscapes across the 55 km’s that I doubt no other trail would be able to match. We will definitely be returning to hike the trail again!
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 22:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/laugavegur-iceland</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/laugavegur-iceland</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
